Today's דף daf is ל"ז. Lamed Zayin. We pick up at the
very top of ל"ז עמוד א' Lamed Zayin Amud Aleph and the
issue that we had been dealing with is the question about
when
would we force a divorce in certain circumstances where somebody married against
a rabbinic concern. So the case had been we had brought in
an issue by a digression about not marrying a woman who was
pregnant or nursing of a child of another man who had been
divorced from or who had been widowed or had died. And if
one did, one needed to separate or actually divorce until the woman
had finished nursing and then remarry. And the question would be what
would be the story if that was a כהן kohen that marriage
would not be possible? And the גמרא Gemara sort of compared this
to a similar discussion about a woman who is a יבמה yevama
who is a sister-in-law and there was a child and the child
died within thirty days and it wasn't clear. According to רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, that was a question whether it
was a viable child or not. I should note two things by
the way about that: one that I noted yesterday, which is that
the question is only if it was not a full-term pregnancy. The
other point is that we're dealing with the child died as a
result of let's say some tragedy,
like he fell off of a building or whatever, God forbid, something
of that nature. If it was a more natural death within thirty
days, that might be evidence to the fact that the child was
not viable. But the child died within thirty days and there remains
a question whether it was viable, remains a question whether the mother
was exempt from חליצה chalitza or not. And she went ahead and
remarried. And the question is: do we demand חליצה? chalitza? Is she
married a כהן kohen because if we demand חליצה chalitza at this
stage, then she will be forbidden to her husband. So there there
was the opinion that there would be that the possibility that we
would not demand חליצה. chalitza. So the question would be: what about
our case by the man who married this woman who was still
nursing? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: הכא, hacha, well, three lines from the top, yes,
the basic issue is whether the man's deceased fathered a child. Why
is it important whether it's a full-term child or nursing?
No, full-term would just be evidence that it was a that we
would assume that it was viable. If the child was born, if
it was a viable child who died later, then the mother is
exempt from יבום. yibbum. If it was never a viable child, then
the mother is obligated to יבום. yibbum. So if it was a
full-term child, then we just presume that it was viable. If it
was not a full-term child, then we need thirty days before we
could assume viability.
Oh, full-term child doesn't require the thirty days?
Correct. Even according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
correct. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא, hacha, top of ל"ז עמוד
א', Lamed Zayin Amud Aleph, three lines from the
top, הכא גבי מעוברת חבירו ומינקת חבירו דנישאת לכהן מאי? hacha gabei
me'uberet chaveiro umineket chaveiro deniseit lekohen mai? Here by the case of
a woman who is nursing or pregnant and marries to somebody else,
what's the story if she married a כהן? kohen? מי עבדי רבנן
תקנתא לכהן או לא? mi avdi Rabbanan takanta lekohen o lo? Did
they do something to help the כהן kohen in this case and
not demand divorce or not? Because anyway he'll be allowed to remarry
if he weren't a כהן kohen after this period is over. So
אמר ליה הכי השתא? amar lei hachi hashta? He said how could
you compare those two cases? בשלמא התם, bishlama hatam, it makes sense
in the case where we don't demand it when the infant died
within thirty days and she went ahead and remarried and she married
a כהן. kohen. כיון דאיכא רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
keivan de'ika Rabbanan dephaligi aleih deRabban Shimon ben Gamliel, since there's the
Rabbis that argue on Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, דאמרי אף על גב
דלא שהה, de'amri af al gav dela shaha, even if he didn't
wait thirty days, ולד מעליא הוא, velad malya hu, we can assume
the child was viable. So therefore,
גבי אשת כהן, gabei eishet kohen, by the wife of a כהן,
kohen, כיון דלא אפשר, keivan dela efshar, that it would be not
possible to demand חליצה—meaning chalitza obviously it would be possible, but then
it would have you know profound consequences, wouldn't be possible for them
to stay married if we demanded חליצה—עבדינן כרבנן, we rely on the
Rabbis. So basically we're not just waiving the criteria, oh okay you're
married to a כהן kohen so חליצה chalitza would be too big
of a deal so forget חליצה. chalitza We're not saying that. We're
saying because you're married to a כהן, kohen, we'll rely on the
position of the רבנן Rabbanan who say that the child was definitely
viable. So therefore we actually have a position to rely upon. And
that we will use that opinion when we need to. Meaning it's
like a statement in the גמרא Gemara you know, כדי הוא פלוני
לסמוך עליו בשעת הדחק. kedai hu ploni lismokh alav bish'at hadechak. So
we can assume we can rely on a minority opinion here, it's
not even a minority opinion, it's רבנן Rabbanan against רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel when we need to because otherwise she
would have to divorce her husband. That makes sense. אבל הכא, aval
hacha, here by the case of the pregnant or nursing woman, כמאן
עבדינן? keman abdinnan? Who should we go like? There's no opinion that
says you don't need to get a divorce. אי רבי מאיר, ei
Rabbi Meir, אמר יוציא ולא יחזיר עולמית. amar yotzi velo yachzir olamit.
Rabbi Meir says get a divorce and never remarry.
ואי רבנן, ve'ei Rabbanan, הא אמרי בגט, ha amri beget, they say
that you have to get a divorce even if you could remarry
later. So meaning we are not going to say that just cause
he's a כהן kohen we're going to waive the requirement. We might
say we can rely on a minority opinion but we're not going
to say we can waive the requirement. And since here both. And
since here both Rabbi Meir and the רבנן Rabbanan demand a גט,
get, we're going to demand it here even in the case of
כהן. Kohen. That's interesting. You know sometimes we do make exceptions, we
don't need a minority opinion to rely on. Here the גמרא Gemara
is saying, not necessarily and it would really be amazing. A כהן
Kohen married a woman who was still nursing? Totally legitimate marriage, it
was just, you know, she was just still nursing for a baby.
We according to this, there's no question according to all opinions we
would demand a divorce and they would not be able to get
remarried because he was a כהן. Kohen. Okay, איתמר, Itmar, it was
taught, another case about getting married where they shouldn't have. קידש בתוך
שלשה וברח. Kiddesh b'toch shlosha u'varach. Not a case about nursing, a
normal case that a man gets divorced, excuse me, that a woman
gets divorced or a woman is widowed, and what's the הלכה? halacha?
She's supposed to wait three months before remarrying. Why is she supposed
to wait three months before remarrying?
So you don't, so you know whose child it is. And so
she doesn't wait the three months.
But we didn't do נישואין nissu'in though, he said קידושין.
kiddushin. Fine, okay, one second. You went ahead and you had קידושין,
kiddushin, it doesn't matter, you're not supposed to do, right, let's take
a look. So you went ahead and you did קידושין, kiddushin, you're
supposed to wait three months. Michael points out of course the real
problem is נישואין, nissu'in, not the קידושין. kiddushin. So let's see what
happened. So he went ahead and he married her within the three
months. וברח, U'varach, and then he ran away. Okay, not exactly clear
why he's running away, maybe he's running away because he knows he
doesn't want to force us maybe to cause him to divorce his
wife or something, okay, or he's avoiding the wedding. Okay, so what's
the הלכה? halacha? פליגי בה רב אחא ורפראם. Pligi bah Rav Acha
v'Rafram. So רב אחא Rav Acha and רפראם Rafram debate. חד אמר
משמתינן ליה, Chad amar meshamtinan lei, the one said that we put
him in חרם cherem until he divorces his wife. Again, the assumption
is that if somebody gets married even קידושין kiddushin within the three
months, we would force a divorce. Okay, וחד אמר, v'chad amar, and
the other one says, ערוקי מסתייה, arukei mistayei,
his running away suffices, meaning, since he's run away, clearly he is
not about to do נישואין. nissu'in. And since as Michael correctly points
out, the concern here is the נישואין nissu'in because there's a concern
about if she gets pregnant whose child it is, so since it's
clear that he's not going to do נישואין nissu'in anytime soon or
else he wouldn't have run away, we do not have to go
ahead and find him and force a גט get in this case.
הוה עובדא, Havei uvda, there was a case, רמיה לרפרם, ramia l'Rafram,
and רפרם Rafram said exactly what he said here in an actual
practical case, ערוקי מסתייה, arukei mistayei, it's enough that he ran away.
So if somebody goes ahead and does קידושין kiddushin within three months,
now of course nowadays the question has been raised, of course, you
can go ahead and do a pregnancy test. Okay, fine, but anyway,
this would be a question about, you know, the guy would be
well advised to just run away somewhere, especially if he was a
כהן, Kohen, or else we would force a גט get and then
we wouldn't be able to remarry, but here just running away suffices.
Now the question is what about the case in a similar issue
about מינקת חבירו meineket chaveiro and מעוברת חבירו muberet chaveiro if it
was just קידושין kiddushin and not נישואין? nissu'in? Since until now the
גמרא Gemara sounded like there's no option, you gotta do a גט
get even in the case of a כהן, Kohen, it only raises
this, you know, other concern about the three months, but not by
the previous one, you would say that there case we would presumably
force a גט get and maybe even he ran away we would
force a גט. get. So תוספות Tosafot introduces, has a very interesting
קולא. kula. If you look back on ל"ו עמוד ב', Lamed Vav
amud bet, where תוספות Tosafot says like this,
the very like three lines before the middle-sized lines, at the narrowest
lines in תוספות, Tosafot, three lines before it gets middle-sized, so in
the תוספות Tosafot at the low, he says, והרב רבי יוסף מאורלינ"ש
v'haRav Rabbi Yosef m'Orlinesh טיהר מטעם זה teher mita'am zeh באחד שקידש
מינקת חבירו, b'echad shekiddesh meineket chaveiro, a man did קידושין kiddushin with
a woman who was still
nursing, שלא להצריך גט, shelo l'hatzrich get, because the גמרא, Gemara, right,
is pretty heavy, גט get even in the case of a כהן,
Kohen, אלא הפרשה בעלמא, Ela hafrasha b'alma, since there was only קידושין
kiddushin not
נישואין, nissu'in, כיון דבלאו הכי אסורא ליה, keivan d'belav hachi assura lei,
since anyway they're not going to be having sex, how do you
know they're not going to be having sex and that was the
whole problem, דכלה בלא ברכה אסורה לבעלה כנדה d'kallah belo bracha assura
l'ba'alah k'niddah because they haven't had שבע ברכות, Sheva Brachot, they haven't
had נישואין. nissu'in. So he basically said, since it's just קידושין, kiddushin,
you don't need to give a גט, get, you can just separate.
Okay, and then he goes ahead and tries to fit it in
with the later גמרא Gemara that said like only in a case
when he ran away and even there it says only in the
case of the three months wait, not in the case of the
nursing mother, but nevertheless you see, you know, that these are very
heavy demands that the גמרא Gemara is placing, so there is an
attempt in some of the בעלי התוספות Ba'alei haTosafot to find certain
leniencies and one of them would be קידושין kiddushin without נישואין. nissu'in.
Okay, back to our case on ל"ז, Lamed Zayin, two dots. Okay,
now we get to a fun section of the גמרא Gemara about
somebody who does not know, right, this woman went ahead and she
did יבום yibbum with the brother-in-law, and then she had a child,
and it was not known whether this child was the child of
the, because she didn't wait three months, and it wasn't known whether
this child was her first husband's son or second husband's son. Now
if it's her first husband's son and she's now living with the
brother-in-law, that's an איסור כרת, issur kares, so you better stop living
with the brother. But what's the... the status of the child? Well,
the child isn't a ממזר mamzer either way. Either he's the first
brother's son, so fine, he's the first brother's son, you know, a
legitimate child. Or he's not the first brother's son, which means that
the other brother did a legitimate יבום, yibum, which means that he's
also a legitimate child. So either way, he doesn't know who his
father is, but he does know that he's not a ממזר, mamzer,
okay?
So let's take a look.
All right, so anyway, we're not worrying about that now. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן. Amar
lei Rava l'Rav Nachman. So Rava said to Rav Nachman, לימא, Leima,
I don't get it. Why do we not know who the father
is? Let's say הלך אחר רוב נשים. Halach achar rov nashim. Let's
go by most women. רוב נשים לתשעה ילדן Rov nashim l'tisha yaldan
and most women give birth after nine months cause the whole story
was, this woman gave birth let's say seven months after she did
יבום yibum possible יבום yibum with the brother-in-law. Okay, so we say
okay and then she gives a birth. What's more likely? Is this
more likely that this child is a seven month baby or a
nine month baby? More likely, it's a nine month baby and therefore
the first guy is the father. Okay. So why do we not
know, why can we not assume who the father is? So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
And by the way, רש"י Rashi says one of the consequences, we're
going to see a lot of our גמרא Gemara is going to
be dealing with the consequence of like who inherits from whom, you
know, knowing who the father is to know who gets whose property.
But רש"י Rashi says the other implication is that if we assume
that it is the first guy's child, then we'll know for certain
that there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum and they're definitely doing
a, you know, prohibited act here, an עריות, arayos, and they should
bring a definite חטאת, chatas, a חטאת קבוע. chatas kavua. The משנה
Mishnah said they only bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Maybe they
did an איסור כרת, isur kareis, maybe they didn't. The גמרא Gemara
is saying let's just take it for granted that it's the first
guy's son and they're definitely in violation and they should be bringing
a definite חטאת. chatas. So why can't we just assume it's the
first guy's son? Yeah.
It just struck me in socio-emotional context, this seems they're doing יבום
yibum within a week or two of the death of the...
Oh, it could be up to, it could be up to three
months because that's
why you had the seven/nine months...
No, you have like a, because the גמרא Gemara assumes that a
baby could be born viable after six months and two days.
So basically you could have waited, you know, two and three quarters
months, done יבום, yibum, and then the baby is born in six
months and two days and, you know, so that's the scenario. Yeah.
Isn't אשם תלוי asham talui used when you're not sure if you
sinned or not and you're going to find out eventually and then
you bring a חטאת?
chatas? No, when you find out eventually you'll bring the חטאת, chatas,
but it doesn't have to be that you have the possibility of
finding out eventually, that's not necessarily. Yeah, now there is a question
whether you need חתיכה משתי חתיכות, chaticha mishtei chatichos, but we won't
get to that. Okay. So גמרא Gemara says like this.
So anyway, why don't we just assume it's the first guy's son
for and all the implications.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him,
נשי דידן בשבעה ילדן. Nashei didan beshiva yaldan.
Our women give birth after, you know, after seven months, which means
like even into the seventh
month, six months, six months and two days. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so Rava said back to him, נשי דידכו הוו רובא דעלמא? Nashei
didichu havu ruba d'alma? Who cares? So since when are the women
in your town the majority of the world? It's still there's still
a majority of women give birth after nine months and even if
you were to say that there's a, there's a, you know, defined
minority that give birth, you know, in six months or seven months,
still why not go by the majority? So he said oh no,
here's what I mean. אמר ליה, Amar lei, הכי קאמינא. Hachi ka'amina.
Here's what I'm trying to say. רוב נשים ילדן לתשעה. Rov nashim
yaldan l'tisha. I can see that most women give birth after nine.
ומיעוטא לשבעה. U'miyuta l'shiva. But there's a non-trivial minority that give birth
even after seven or actually in the seventh month according to the
גמרא. Gemara. Now there's another thing to consider. וכל היולדת לתשעה עוברה
ניכר לשליש ימיה. V'chol hayoledes l'tisha ubra nikar l'shlish yameha. Any woman
who gives birth in nine months, after three months, you know, you'll
be able to see that she's pregnant, she'll be visibly pregnant. Now
if this woman were visibly pregnant after three months, what would happen?
She had went ahead and did יבום yibum with the brother-in-law, let's
say at the end of two months, a month later you would
have seen her visibly pregnant. So you would have had no doubt
who the father was, right? You would have okay she's visibly pregnant
after one month of marrying this guy, obviously it's the first guy's
kid. Since there's a doubt who the father is, there must be
another thing not said in the משנה Mishnah but implicitly, that she
was not visibly pregnant after three months of the other guy's death.
She remained non-visibly pregnant. Well, that's another factor to consider here. On
the one hand you're right, most women after nine months. On the
other hand, this woman was not visibly pregnant within the first three
months of the guy's death. So that's evidence that maybe she isn't
pregnant from the first guy. וזו הואיל ולא הוכר עוברה לשליש ימיה,
V'zu ho'il v'lo hukeir ubra l'shlish yameha, since this one she was
not visibly pregnant a third into the pregnancy from the first guy,
three months after the death of the first guy, because if she
was we would have known what the story was, איתרע לה רובא.
itrei lah ruba. So now the majority is thrown into suspect. On
the one hand the majority is is that you know it's a
nine month baby, on the other hand we have now some serious
questions about that because three months in it was not yet evident.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. says, that's an excellent
answer. So the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute. אי כל היולדת
לתשעה ועוברה ניכר לששה מהא? Ei kol hayoledet l'tisha u'vra nikkar l'shisha
meha? The גמרא Gemara is going to be very exact here. Wait
a minute, you said every woman who gives birth in nine days
it's evident after three months? If every woman it's evident after three
months, so we have an evidence that's the exact opposite. הא מדלא
אינכר לשלישא מהא, Ha me'delo u'kar l'shlisha meha, this woman since three
months after the first guy's death it was not yet evident, ועוברה,
u'v'ra, so ודאי בר שבע לבתרא הוא. vadai bar sheva l'vastra hu.
Certainly it's the second guy's. Right? You said every woman will know
after three months. Okay, so this one you didn't know after three
months, clearly it's the second guy's. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara said,
okay, I didn't mean every. אלא אימא, רוב Ela eima rov. היולדת
לתשעה ועוברה ניכר לששה מהא. Most of the time if it's a
nine month pregnancy it's visible after three months. והאי מדלא אינכר לשלישא
מהא, V'hai me'delo u'kar l'shlisha meha, since it's not visible after three
months, איתרע ליה רובא, itre lah ruba, the majority is thrown into
question, the majority that most babies are nine month babies. So you
see it's an excellent answer, right? It's like, let's figure it out.
Okay, you have a baby, you don't know who it's from. Most
likely it's a nine month baby, it's from the first guy. On
the other hand, the counterweighing evidence is that if it were from
the first guy, you would have seen it, she would have been
visibly pregnant after three months. Not always, but the majority of the
time. So we have these counterweighing facts. So therefore, that's why it's
a ספק. safek. Okay, excellent answer. So now let's take a look
what the גמרא Gemara says. One minute.
אלא אימא Ela eima, רוב. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan,
our Rabbis taught: ראשון ראוי להיות כהן גדול. Rishon ra'uy lihyot kohen
gadol. The first kid born after the יבום yibum and within nine
months from the first guy and seven months from the second guy,
so we don't know who the father is, but if both brothers
are כהנים, kohanim, which obviously if one is a כהן kohen the
other is a כהן, kohen, so then this kid is a completely
unquestionable כהן. kohen. And therefore he can even be a כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. It's true you don't know who the father is, but
he was born legitimately, either from the first guy, or if he
wasn't the first guy, then it was a legitimate יבום yibum and
he's born from the second guy. So this guy, the first guy
could be a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Okay, now תוספות Tosafot raises
a question that even if you know someone is a kosher כהן,
kohen, you know there's a גמרא Gemara that says that we want
him to be a כהן מיוחס, kohen miyuchas, to know who the
father is. Okay, but תוספות Tosafot says well, maybe you don't have
to know who the father is, maybe that's only if there's a
question if it was, you know, he was born out of an
extramarital affair. But if this guy was definitely born in the context
of marriage, you just don't know the first marriage or the second
marriage, then he's totally a good כהן, kohen, he can even be
a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. ראשון ראוי להיות כהן גדול. Rishon ra'uy
lihyot kohen gadol. ושני ממזר מספק. V'sheni mamzer misafek. But the second
kid is a doubtful ממזר. mamzer. What is the second kid? The
woman stayed married to the brother-in-law, okay, and then she had another
kid. So she stayed married to the brother-in-law, so that might be
an איסור כרת, isur kares, right? This kid might be from the
first marriage, there's no מצווה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, brother-in-law is an
ערווה, ervah, right? And the kid would be a ממזר. mamzer. So
while the first kid is definitely okay, either the first father's kid
and therefore totally okay, or if he wasn't the first father's kid
there was a מצווה יבום mitzvah yibum and therefore the second father's
kid but okay, a kid that comes later could be a ממזר
mamzer if the first one was the first father's, no מצווה יבום,
mitzvah yibum, the second one will be a ממזר. mamzer. So the
first one could be a כהן גדול kohen gadol and the second
one is a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. Is that clear? Okay fine.
So רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer, Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov says, what? Yeah, be an interesting Thanksgiving dinner you
said, that's hilarious. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
omer, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says אין ממזר מספק. ein mamzer misafek.
There's no ממזר mamzer from doubt. Now what does that mean? Wow.
Nobody can disagree with the fact he's a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer.
So it must be a debate of the law of how do
you deal with the הלכה halacha of ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. And
this is a really important question. So let's take a look. מאי
קאמר? Mai kama? What is he saying? אמר אביי הכי קאמר, Amar
Abaye hachi kama, this is what he's saying. ראשון ראוי להיות כהן
גדול, Rishon ra'uy lihyot kohen gadol, ושני ספק ממזר. v'sheni safek mamzer.
So the first opinion that says he's a doubtful ממזר, mamzer, what's
the consequences of that? ואסור בממזרת. v'asur b'mamzeret. A doubtful ממזר mamzer
could be the worst place to be. A ממזר mamzer can't marry,
right, a
ישראל, Yisrael, ישראלית. Yisraelit. Okay. But who can a ממזר mamzer marry?
Another ממזרת. mamzeret. א ממזרת, a mamzeret, correct. All right, fine. So
if he's a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, can't marry a ממזרת mamzeret
because maybe he's a non-ממזר. mamzer. He can't marry a non-ממזר mamzer
because maybe he's a ממזר. mamzer. Okay, so being a doubtful ממזר
mamzer is the worst of the...
He can marry no one? No,
he can marry a convert.
That's it. Okay, because... okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וספק ממזר ואסור בממזרת, v'safek mamzer v'asur b'mamzeret, can't marry not
only not marry a normal ישראל Yisrael but can't even marry a
ממזרת. mamzeret. He's caught in both ends. רבי אליעזר אומר אינו ספק
ממזר, Rabbi Eliezer omer eino safek mamzer, we don't treat him like
a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. Yes you're right, I agree to the
facts he's a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, but I don't agree to
the הלכה halacha category ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. How you treat a
ספק ממזר? safek mamzer? אלא ודאי ממזר ומותר בממזרת. Ela vadai mamzer
u'mutar b'mamzeret. Now he's not saying that those are the facts. He's
saying that the הלכה halacha is that
a
but somebody who is in a questionable personal status like a ממזר,
mamzer, that is not at that ממזר mamzer can marry. Why? Because
let's understand let's explain for example the פסוק pasuk is learned out
by לא יבא ממזר lo yavo mamzer you know בקהל ה', bikhal
Hashem, בקהל ה', bikhal Hashem, which is basically like understood as you
know the untainted מיוחס meyuchas type of a community. So therefore the
idea is somebody who is a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, you know
what, in fact he might actually be not a ממזר mamzer and
totally like untainted. But the fact that he has a doubtful status,
that already takes him out of the untainted category. The question mark
over his head puts him into the you know gray area. And
once he's in the gray area it's okay for him to marry
a ממזר mamzer and a ממזר mamzer to marry him or her,
right, whether it whoever whichever one is the ממזר. mamzer. So when
he's saying אינו ספק ממזר, eino safek mamzer, he's saying I'm not
saying that a ישראל Yisrael can marry him, of course not or
her, right, of course not, because it might be a ממזר. mamzer.
But another ממזר mamzer can marry a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. Okay,
and that's what he means אינו ספק ממזר, eino safek mamzer, meaning
it's not in this problematic status of ספק, safek, it's in at
least a more black and white position we'll treat him as if
he's as if he's a full ממזר. mamzer. אלא ודאי ממזר ומותר
בממזרת. ela vaday mamzer u'muttar be'mamzeret. That's what אביי Abaye says. Okay,
so that is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov being
lenient. רבא Rava is going to say the same thing except he's
going to reverse it. רבא אמר הכי קאמר, Rava amar hachi ka'amar,
this is how you read it. אמר ראשון ראוי להיות כהן גדול,
Amar rishon ra'uy liyot Kohen Gadol, the first one could be a
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, ושני ממזר ודאי מספק ומותר בממזרת. ve'sheni mamzer
vaday misafek u'muttar be'mamzeret. You gotta love that. ממזר ודאי מספק. Mamzer
vaday misafek. So what the גמרא Gemara says the second one is
a ממזר מספק. mamzer misafek. He doesn't mean he doesn't say the
second one is a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. The second one is
a ממזר, mamzer, we'll treat him as a ממזר, mamzer,
מספק, misafek, resulting from the doubt we're going to treat him as
a ממזר. mamzer. Interesting way of reading the words, right? You get
it? It didn't say the second guy is a ספק ממזר. safek
mamzer. The second guy is a ממזר mamzer as a result of
the ספק. safek. Same idea except reversing the positions. So according to
this the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying we treat him as
a ודאי
ממזר vaday mamzer ושני ממזר מספק... ve'sheni mamzer misafek...
where am I
hold on... ודאי מספק ומותר בממזרת vaday misafek u'muttar be'mamzeret and can
marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר אין ודאי ממזר
מספק. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer ein vaday mamzer misafek. We do
not have a ודאי ממזר vaday mamzer status resulting from doubt. אלא
ספק ממזר, ela safek mamzer, his status is a
ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, ואסור בממזרת ve'asur be'mamzeret and can't marry a
ממזרת. mamzeret. So it's the exact same debate except reversing who says
which. Okay, but this is a question of can a ספק ממזר
safek mamzer מותר בממזרת muttar be'mamzeret marry a
ממזרת. mamzeret. דקמיפלגי בדרבי אלעזר, de'kamiflgi be'de'Rabbi Elazar, they debate the position
of רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. דתנן רבי אלעזר אומר,
detnan Rabbi
Elazar omer,
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says, ודאן בודאן מותר, vadan be'vadan muttar,
a ודאי ממזר vaday mamzer can marry a ודאי ממזר. vaday mamzer.
ודאן בספיקן וספיקן בודאן, vadan bi'sfekan u'sfekan be'vadan,
a ודאי ממזר vaday mamzer marrying a ספק safek or a ספק
safek marrying a ודאי, vaday, same point except who's the man and
who's the woman, וספיקן בספיקן u'sfekan be'sfekan or a ספק ממזר safek
mamzer marrying a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, אסור, asur, okay, is forbidden
because you understand why even a ספק safek in a ספק safek
is forbidden, because one ספק safek might be might be you know
one category and the other might be the other category. Now I
said ממזר mamzer but he's really referring to all the people of
problematic status. Okay, the point is they can only marry a ודאי
vaday with a ודאי. vaday. A ספק safek with a ספק safek
or you know a ספק safek with a ודאי vaday is not
you can't, you have to be concerned that it's the wrong category
and it's a problem. ואלו הן ספיקן, ve'elu hen sfekan, and this
is the case of the doubts of who of who's who. שתוקי
Shtuki ואסופי ve'Asufi וכותי. ve'Kuti. A שתוקי Shtuki is the kid that
he says to his mommy, mommy where's daddy, who's daddy? She says
just shut up. So okay, so that's שתוקי. Shtuki. So so I
guess a single mother who you don't know who the father is.
אסופי Asufi is a kid gathered in from the outside, meaning a
foundling, similar but as opposed to you know who the mother is
this is a kid that's like left you know at the שול
shul steps. Okay, so that's the אסופי. Asufi. So again you don't
know who the
who you don't know who the father is. What? You don't mother
or the father. And כותי Kuti is a Samaritan and the issue
with the Samaritans is since they have different rules in terms of
what הלכתית קידושין halachically kiddushin and what's not הלכתית קידושין halachically kiddushin
they could think a woman isn't married when she is and the
child will be a ממזר. mamzer. So you have to treat all
Samaritans as ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim. But certainly when you don't know
who the father is or you don't and certainly if you don't
know the father or the mother then if you don't know who
the parents are we might be dealing with a ממזר. mamzer. Those
are cases of ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. And he says in those
cases one of them cannot marry the other because one might be
a ממזר mamzer and the other might not. So that's saying ספק
ממזר safek mamzer is אסור. asur. Okay.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב, ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, and רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of רב, Rav, הלכה כרבי
אלעזר, halacha ke'Rabbi Elazar, we rule like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that
ספק ממזר safek mamzer is אסור. asur. כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל, ki
amrita kamei de'Shmuel, but רב יהודה Rav Yehuda learned both from רב
Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said when I
said this to שמואל Shmuel that רב Rav said a ספק ממזר
safek mamzer was אסור, asur, so אמר לי, amar li, he said
to
me, הלל שנה
עשרה יוחסין.
Hillel shana
asara yuchasin. genealogical classes. We'll just say יוחסין. yuchsin. Okay, there are
ten categories of lineage or whatever that came from בבל. Bavel. Okay,
not not all that you would say is מיוחס, meyuchas, ten from
well מיוחס meyuchas to not well מיוחס meyuchas that came from בבל.
Bavel. Here they are.
כהני לוי וישראלי. Kohane Levi v'Yisraeli. כהנים לויים ישראלים. Kohanim Levi'im Yisraelim.
חללי, Chalale, חלל, chalal, which is a כהן Kohen who has lost
his קדושת כהונה, kedushas kehunah, like he was the offspring of a
כהן Kohen and a גרושה. grusha. So he might be a כהן
Kohen but he doesn't have any קדושת כהונה kedushas kehunah anymore. גירי,
Geire, convert. חרורי, Cherure, slaves that were freed, משוחרר. meshuchrar. Okay. ממזירי,
Mamzeire,
a ממזר. mamzer. נתיני, Nesinei, נתינים Nesinim are a people that were
put as slaves in the time of, you know, יהושע Yehoshua and
or דוד David or whatever, and anyway they have a questionable... יהושע,
Yehoshua, and they have a questionable status about whether they are like
Jewish or not. Okay. שתוקי, Shetuki, right? The kid who has a
single mother and you don't know who the father is. ואסופי v'Asufi
and the foundling. Okay, so going from כהנים Kohanim to ספק ממזר.
safek mamzer. Wait, what about the כותים?
Kutim? Where do they...
I don't know, they weren't עלו מבבל, alu mi'Bavel, they were already
there. וכולן מותרים
לבוא
זה בזה, v'chulan mutarin lavo zeh ba'zeh, and all of them can
intermarry. Now it doesn't mean all of them can intermarry, it doesn't
mean a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can marry a כהן. Kohen. It
means that you will find pairings where one can marry the other.
So כהן לוי ישראלי, Kohein Levi Yisrael, you know, can marry obviously
the other and גרים geirim and so on, you know, but how
about and you know a וודאי ממזר vadai mamzer can marry a
וודאי ממזר. vadai mamzer. It's interesting ממזר mamzer here isn't mentioned. Oh
yeah, ממזירי, Mamzeire, there was... did I skip over that? וודאי ממזר.
vadai mamzer. Okay, but who can the ספק ממזרים safek mamzers marry?
וודאי ממזר vadai mamzer can marry a וודאי ממזר, vadai mamzer, וודאי
ממזר vadai mamzer can marry a גר, ger, but who could the
ספקים safeks marry? Who could the שתוקי Shetuki and the ואסופי v'Asufi
marry? It must mean that a ספק safek is allowed to marry
a ממזר וודאי, mamzer vadai, right? According to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and position, a ספק safek can't marry anyone. All right. So he
says like this, he says,
yeah, so that's interesting. So רש"י Rashi says,
yeah, why isn't that mentioned? Hold on.
I think because we say that we're talking only that like only
juxtaposed ones can intermarry, like it's not like you wouldn't have to
jump over ממזר mamzer to get to the גרים. geirim. Okay, the
גמרא Gemara is assuming that like only ones that are grouped like
alongside one another, right? Michael asks a good question, right? Because ספק
ממזר safek mamzer could marry a גר, ger, so you would... but
you have ממזר mamzer and then
נתיני שתוקי ואסופי. Nesini Shetuki v'Asufi. So you can't jump over ממזר
mamzer to get to the גר ger category. Okay, so the question
is, וכולן מותרים לבוא זה בזה ואת אמרת הלכה כרבי אליעזר, v'chulan
mutarin lavo zeh ba'zeh v'at amarta halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer, and you're saying
we rule like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's clear that a ספק
safek has to be marry... able to marry at least another ספק,
safek, if not also a real ממזר mamzer according to הלל. Hillel.
So therefore we have this debate, how do we rule? Do we
rule like a ספק ממזר safek mamzer is מותר בממזרת muttar b'mamzeres
or אסור בממזרת? assur b'mamzeres? We have according to the הלל'ס Hillel's
teaching presumably they should be מותר, muttar, according to רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi
Eliezer's teaching they should be אסור. assur. And that's the issue. So
that's why we have a debate of how to interpret this debate
of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and the חכמים.
Chachamim. So אביי סבר לה כשמואל, Abaye savar lah k'Shmuel, אביי Abaye
holds like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר הלכה כהלל, d'amar halacha k'Hillel, we rule
like הלל Hillel and therefore a ספק ממזר safek mamzer is מותר
בממזרת. muttar b'mamzeres. ומוקי לה לרבי אליעזר בן יעקב אליבא דהלכתא, u'muki
lah l'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov aliba d'hilchesa, and for some reason it's
not clear why אביי Abaye and רבא Rava both want to פסקן
pasken like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. So since
אביי Abaye holds like שמואל, Shmuel, holds like הלל, Hillel, that says
it's מותר, muttar, he wants רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov to be the one saying it's מותר. muttar. כי היכי דלא
תקשי הלכתא אהלכתא, ki heichi d'lo tikshi hilchesa ahilchesa, so you wouldn't
have a problem, how could it be that we פסקן pasken like
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and at the same
time פסקן pasken like הלל? Hillel? So he wants רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov to be like the הלכה halacha to
say it's מותר, muttar, and he's the one that says ספק ממזר'ס
safek mamzer's okay and it's the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says
it's a problem. רבא סבר לה כרב, Rava savar lah k'Rav, רבא
Rava holds the other position, דאמר הלכה כרבי אליעזר, d'amar halacha k'Rabbi
Eliezer, we rule like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, not רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that ספק ממזר
safek mamzer is אסור. assur. ומוקי לה לרבי אליעזר בן יעקב אליבא
דהלכתא, u'muki lah l'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov aliba d'hilchesa, and therefore he
reverses the position, that רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
should be saying אסור assur to go like the הלכה halacha that
ספק ממזר'ס safek mamzer's אסור, assur, כי היכי דלא תקשי הלכתא אהלכתא,
ki heichi d'lo tikshi hilchesa ahilchesa,
there shouldn't be a contradiction about the two ways we פסקן. pasken.
I have to tell you, I don't know why he assumes that
we פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
But anyway, what we have here is is the debate of is
ספק ממזר safek mamzer מותר muttar or not, and we have a
clearly that's at the root of the debate of רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and the חכמים, Chachamim, not clear who
says what. So אביי Abaye and רבא Rava interpret it according to
the way they פסקן, pasken, assuming that we're going to פסקן pasken
like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, that's the way
they interpret the debate. So it's a debate about how do we
פסקן pasken about
a
ספק. safek. When he says מותר זה בזה, mutar zeh bezeh, it
doesn't mean everyone can marry every other one. He means that there
are sub-groupings along that list that can marry within one another. Right?
So Ben Hillel, yeah, sounds like it.
I know, I know, that's why it's important. And if you have,
right, כהן, לוי, ישראל, Kohen Levi Yisrael. what was it? חלל, Chalal,
גר, Ger, no first it is גר, משוחרר, Ger Meshuchrar right, and
then ממזר, Mamzer,
נתיני, Netini,
שתוקי, Shtuki,
אסופי. Asufi.
So he says you can make groupings that's מותר זה בזה, mutar
zeh bezeh, right? So you could like, you know, you could like
this group is מותר זה בזה, mutar zeh bezeh, right? And like
this group is מותר זה בזה. mutar zeh bezeh. If you say
that a ספק safek is מותר mutar with a ממזר ודאי. mamzer
vadai.
Male כהן Kohen, can't marry a convert.
כהן לוי ישראל.
Kohen Levi Yisrael When you
leave
ישראל, Yisrael, חלל, Chalal, גר, Ger, right.
Thank you. If it's a male כהן, Kohen you're correct. Thank you.
Okay, thank you, okay. And you've got, right, so you've got that
group, you've got this group is מותר זה בזה, mutar zeh bezeh,
right? You've got, you've got this group is מותר זה בזה, mutar
zeh bezeh, you've got, right, you've got
this group, right, is מותר זה בזה, mutar zeh bezeh, right? Okay,
so you've got different, you have different sub-groupings
that are מותר זה בזה. mutar zeh bezeh. Right?
All these can marry one another. ישראל חלל גר משוחרר Yisrael Chalal
Ger Meshuchrar can marry one another. גר משוחרר ממזר נתין, Ger Meshuchrar
Mamzer Netin, actually this should be bigger. No, that's
right, because right,
this can marry one another. Okay, ממזר נתיני שתוקי ואסופי Mamzer Netini
Shtuki ve-Asufi can marry one another. I guess actually wait, this group
might extend all the way here if you say ספק ממזר safek
mamzer
is מותר, mutar, right. If you say ספק ממזר safek mamzer is
מותר, mutar, then this group extends all the way here, right, if
you say ספק ממזר safek mamzer is מותר. mutar. Okay, because then
they can marry a ממזר mamzer
and marry a גר Ger, and משוחרר Meshuchrar, etc. This is a
ספק ממזר safek mamzer is מותר, mutar, right? So that's how you
get these sort of, you know, you see these like... let me
move this. Okay,
right?
כהן Kohen, לוי Levi, ישראל Yisrael, and חלל Chalal can marry one
another. ישראל חלל גר ומשוחרר Yisrael Chalal Ger u-Meshuchrar can marry one
another. ממזר Mamzer can marry גר Ger משוחרר Meshuchrar etc., and ספק
ממזר, safek mamzer, who can they marry? So if they can marry
ממזר Mamzer and גר Ger and משוחרר, Meshuchrar, right, or they can
marry גר Ger and משוחרר, Meshuchrar, but if they can marry ממזר,
Mamzer, you're good.
If they can't marry ממזר, Mamzer, then there's nobody they can marry.
I mean they can marry גר, Ger, but then you'd have to
like jump over these people in the list.
Okay, is that somewhat clearer? Yeah, okay. So the point is they
can't everybody marry one another, but you can get sub-groups that can
marry within one another. Okay, let's take a look at top of
ל"ז עמוד ב'. lamed zayin amud bet. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says
אביי, Abaye, מנא אמינא לה דכל ספק לרבי אלעזר בן יעקב
כודאי משוי ליה.
mina amina lei
dechol safek le-Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov kevadai mashvei lei.
Where do I get this idea that every doubt according to רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov is like a ודאי, vadai,
meaning a doubtful ממזר mamzer is like a ודאי ממזר vadai mamzer
and can marry a ודאי ממזר, vadai mamzer, which is a leniency?
דתניא, Detanya, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר: Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer:
הרי שבעל נשים הרבה, Harey sheba'al nashim harbeh,
a man has sex with many women, ואינו יודע איזה מהן בעל,
ve-eino yode'a eyzeh mehen ba'al, and he doesn't know who he had
sex with.
וכן היא שבאו עליה נשים הרבה, Ve-chen hi sheba'u aleha nashim harbeh,
a woman has sex with many men, ואינה יודעת מאיזה מהן קיבלה,
ve-eino yoda'at me-eyzeh mehen kiblah, and she doesn't know which one she
became pregnant by. So basically you have kids in the world who
don't know who their parents are.
נמצא אב נושא את בתו ואח נושא את אחותו, Nimtsa av nosei
et bito ve-ach nosei et achoto, so people don't know who their
parents are, you could have a brother marrying a sister, okay, or
a father marrying a daughter. נתמלא כל העולם כולו ממזרים, Nimleh kol
ha-olam kulo mamzerim, and the world will be and the world will
be filled with ממזרים. mamzerim. ועל זה נאמר, Ve-al zeh ne'emar, based
on this the verse says, ומלאה הארץ זמה, umalah ha-arets zimah, the
world will be filled with, you know, like fornication or, you know,
forbidden sexual activity. So therefore, so that's the importance of obviously knowing
who the parentage is. Now, why is that interesting for us? First
of all, it's important because there's a whole debate about whether
extra-marital sex or pre-marital sex, let's say nobody's married, you know, assuming
also the woman isn't a נדה, niddah, is that forbidden or not?
Is that the prohibition of a prostitute, of קדשה kedeshah anytime it's
not within the context of marriage, that's what the רמב"ם Rambam says,
or is it not? You know, פילגש pilegesh and so on. So
even those that say that it's not, say it's not if it's
done in the context of like a committed relationship, but to just
sort of have, you know, you know, sort of like sleep around,
casual sex with anybody, that's the problem of ומלאה הארץ זמה, umalah
ha-arets zimah, then you don't know who the parent is and so
on. Okay, so that's anyway, that's the purpose of that teaching. What's
interesting for us is that he says the world will be filled
with ממזרים, mamzerim, but it's not going to be filled with ממזרים.
mamzerim. It'll be filled with what? ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim. Yeah. So
he calls them ממזרים mamzerim even though they're ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim.
It's to tell you that that's their halachic category. They're treated like
ממזר ודאי, mamzer vaday, which remember is a leniency. Okay, so that's
he says, that's my proof that Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov treats them
as a ודאי ממזר. vaday mamzer. ורבא אמר לך, ve-Rabba amar lecha,
and רבא Rabba who says that he doesn't treat them like a
ודאי ממזר, vaday mamzer, what would he say? He'll say back to
you: הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's what the verse reads: not זמה,
zimmah, but when he says quotes זמה, zimmah, it's not about sexual
impropriety, but it's
זו מה היא. zo ma hi. זמה, zimmah, it's like a ראשי
תיבות. roshei teivos. Who is this one? So when he says the
what would be filled with ממזר, mamzer, he means ספק ממזר. safek
mamzer. He's not saying halachically ממזר. mamzer. And that's what זמה zimmah
means. You don't know who they are, they might be ממזרים. mamzerim.
Okay. Now before we go on, just a minute about the הלכה
halacha about this. So we actually פוסקין לחומרא. paskin l'chumra. And we
actually פוסקין paskin that a ספק ממזר safek mamzer is אסור בספק
assur bi-safek and אסור בממזרת assur bi-mamzeres and אסור בישראל. assur bi-Yisrael.
We also פוסקין, paskin, by the way, that there's another הלכה halacha
in the opposite way but which has been implicit here, but I'll
just say it, which is what's the סברא s'vara by ישראל Yisrael
by a ספק ממזר? safek mamzer? The גמרא Gemara just
takes for granted that a ישראל Yisrael by a ספק ממזר safek
mamzer is אסור. assur. The only question is maybe a ספק ממזר
safek mamzer is מותר mutar by a ממזרת. mamzeres. Okay, but by
a ממזרת. mamzeres. But let me just read you the רמב"ם Rambam
just so you should know the הלכה. halacha.
And I got the wrong one, excuse me.
Where's
the
רמב"ם? Rambam? Not on your smartphone? I guess it is on my
smartphone.
For once in my office I don't need my smartphone. Okay.
Okay, so the רמב"ם Rambam says like this, let me find it.
דין
תורה פרק ט"ו הלכה כ"א: Din Torah, Perek Tet-Vav Halacha Chaf-Alef: שספק
ממזר מותר לבוא בקהל. she-safek mamzer mutar lavo b'kahal.
So this you wouldn't have known in the גמרא. Gemara.
Wow.
He says דאורייתא d'oraisa speaking,
a ספק ממזר safek mamzer can actually marry ישראל. Yisrael. שנאמר לא
יבוא ממזר בקהל ה'
shene'emar,
'lo yavo mamzer b'kahal Hashem.'
ממזר ודאי אסור לבוא בקהל ולא ספק. mamzer vaday assur lavo b'kahal
v'lo safek. Right,
which is a big leniency. Anytime there's a doubt you could marry,
not a problem. אבל חכמים, aval Chachamim, but rabbinically, the sages עשו
מעלה ביוחסין, asu ma'aleh b'yuchsin, made a higher demand when it comes
to יוחסין, yuchsin, ואסרו גם ספקות לבוא בקהל. v'asru gam sfekos lavo
b'kahal. And
so they can't marry. לפיכך ממזר ודאי מותר לישא ממזרת ודאית. lefichach,
mamzer vaday mutar lisa mamzeres vada'is. A definite ממזר mamzer can marry
another ממזר. mamzer. אבל ממזר ספק ושתוקי ואסופי אסור לישא בת ישראל.
aval mamzer safek u'shtuki v'asufi assur lisa bas Yisrael.
So the first thing is to know that the fact that a
ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry ישראל Yisrael is rabbinic. Okay, דאורייתא
d'oraisa they could. So that's cut out. Now how about them marrying
a ממזר? mamzer? Then he says: ואסור לישא ממזרת, v'assur lisa mamzeres,
ואפילו ממזרת מספק אסורה לו. v'afilu mamzeres mi-safek assura lo. So a
ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't even marry a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer.
שמא אחת מהם אינו ממזר והשני ממזר ודאי. shema achas mehem eino
mamzer v'hasheni mamzer vaday. Okay,
and therefore you're really stuck. So what do you do? So he
says, ואין לספקות אלו תקנה, v'ein li-sfekos elu takanah,
there's nobody they can marry. They can't marry a ספק, safek, they
can't marry a ודאי ממזר, vaday mamzer, can't marry a ודאי ישראל.
vaday Yisrael. אלא שישאו מן הגרים. ela she-yisu min ha-geirim.
Okay, the only person they marry is גרים geirim because גרים geirim
aren't in the category of any of the category essentially. Right. Drink
a גר, geir, marry a גר. geir.
Exactly. But the problem is it doesn't solve the problem forever, because
the last line of the רמב"ם Rambam is: והולד הולך אחר הפגם.
vehavlad holech achar hapgam.
But whether it's the father or the mother that's the ספק ממזר,
safek mamzer, the child is going to have the same status. So
you never really solve the problem. Okay, moving on. Just so you
know how that סוגיא sugya concludes. Next, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Since we're quoting Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Eliezer around issues about certain
sexual improprieties,
let's take a look. יתר על כן אמר רבי אליעזר בן יעקב.
yeter al ken amar Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
goes further, back to the גמרא Gemara here ל"ז עמוד ב'. lamed-zayin
amud bais. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov goes further: לא ישא אדם אשה
ממדינה זו וילך וישא אשה ממדינה אחרת. lo yisa adam isha mi-medinah
zu v'yelech v'yisa isha mi-medinah acheres. A man shouldn't marry one woman
in one country and another woman in another country. שמא יזדווגו זה
לזה, shema yizdavgu zeh l'zeh, because again not a time of telecommunications.
So maybe the kids of one wife will encounter the kids of
another wife and nobody will have any idea that they have the
same father. ונמצא אח נושא את אחותו, venimtza ach nosei es achoso,
and a brother will marry a sister. So it's not enough that
you're
Even if you are having kids in marriage, it has to be
in a context where everybody knows who the father is and don't
go ahead and do it in distant countries, people won't realize they're
related to one another. So the גמרא Gemara says איני, eini, is
this really true? דהא רב כי איקלע לדרשיער, Deha Rav ki ikla
le-Darshier, when רב Rav came to Darshier, famous גמרא, Gemara, מכריז, makhriz,
he would make an announcement. רב Rav would be traveling and he'd
make an announcement and say מאן הויא ליה ליומא, man havya lei
leyoma, who wants to be my wife for the day? Okay? So
that's what he did when he was out of home and he
needed to satisfy his sexual needs, so he married somebody in that
town for the day. רב נחמן Rav Nachman and רב נחמן כי
איקלע לשכנציב, Rav Nachman ki ikla le-Shnichziv, when he came to this
place Shnichziv, מכריז, makhriz,
he would announce and say מאן הויא ליה ליומא, man havya lei
leyoma, who wants to be my wife for today? So how are
they satisfying this? They're having women in different countries and they might
have kids who don't know who their parents are, don't know who
the father is. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that's the גמרא's
Gemara answer, שאני רבנן דפקיע שמייהו. shani rabbanan de-faki'a shemayhu.
No, רבנן rabbanan are very famous. Everybody's going to know, my mother,
yeah, when רב Rav was traveling through this town, my mother was
his wife for the day. So it wasn't just some weird man
I have no idea who my father is. Everybody will know who
their father is in this case and therefore we're not afraid that
a brother will marry a sister. Okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's the answer to that, but
we're not done. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, wait one
minute, והאמר רבא, ve-ha amar Rava, how could this whole case make
sense? Doesn't רבא Rava teach תבועה לינשא, tevu'a linasei, if a woman
was sort of she was
already betrothed, she was מקודשת, mekudeshet, they were planning on waiting getting
married at the end of the year, having the נישואין, nisu'in, but
the husband said, the man said, that's it, let's get married tomorrow,
have the חופה chuppah tomorrow. That's תבועה, tevu'a, like he surprised her
with a sudden demand of נישואין. nisu'in. So you understand the transition
from קידושין kiddushin to נישואין nisu'in is now they're going to be
having sex, now they're going to be living together. So there's a
sudden demand of נישואין, nisu'in, so basically there's like the
unanticipated, she's now going to be realizing she's going to have sex
very soon and therefore
ונתפייסה, ve-nifaysa, if she agreed to it, צריכה לישב שבעה נקיים, tzrikha
leishev shiva neki'im, she has to count seven days and then go
to the מקוה. mikvah. Why? Because the גמרא Gemara assumed that a
woman will spot due to sexual excitement and therefore, now normally in
the context of a marriage where it's a regular part of the
married life, that's not going to happen, but for the first time
and if it was unanticipated, he surprised her and said now, let's
not wait for six months, let's do it tomorrow. So that might
lead to spotting and therefore that sexual excitement, some people say that
the
רבנן rabbanan maybe took their reality about sexual excitement that leads to
seminal emission and sort of assumed that the similar thing was true
for women. But whatever it was, they assumed that it might lead
to spotting and therefore you have to wait seven days because she
might be a נדה. niddah. Okay? That's the הלכה. halacha. So the
גמרא Gemara says if that's the הלכה, halacha, how could they have
done this and said who wants to be my wife for the
day? They would have had to have waited for seven days. Now
if he was visiting the town for two weeks, fine, but he
said who wants to be my wife today? How could he do
that? Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says,
רבנן שלוחי הוו משדרי ומודעי להו. rabbanan shluchei havu meshaderu u-modu lehu.
Yeah, they would actually sort of like the whole they would
send somebody ahead of them to arrange it all and there'd be
seven days lead time so the woman would be able to agree
and then go to the מקוה. mikvah. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'is eima, and
if you want you could say, לרבנן ייחודא בעלמא הוא דמייחדי להו,
le-rabbanan yichuda be-alma hu de-meyachadi lehu, they wouldn't actually have sex, they
would just sort of have ייחוד yichud with the women. דאמר מר,
De-amar mar, אינו דומה מי שיש לו פת בסלו למי שאין לו
פת בסלו, eino domeh mi she-yesh lo pas be-salo le-mi she-ein lo
pas be-salo, it's not similar having bread in your basket to not
having bread in your basket. Knowing that the woman is available helps
them address their sexual urges even if they're not actually having sex.
Of course the problem with this is, how is that considered פת
בסלו pas be-salo if you're not able to act on it? Right?
If it's still forbidden, who cares that the woman is there? And
if it's still forbidden, how could you have ייחוד? yichud? Right? So
it's a very complicated גמרא, Gemara, there are different explanations that the
ראשונים Rishonim say to that to explain this idea of ייחוד. yichud.
Some say that once they're having ייחוד, yichud, if they're not announcing
they're going to be having sex, just announcing they're just going to
have ייחוד yichud together, then you can have sex because then you
don't have that,
then it's sort of more acclimated, it's not as sudden
as the other scenario. Right? The other scenario the problem was the
sudden announcement, let's get married and have sex tonight. Okay? This way
it's
like
דוד David and אבישג. Avishag. We're not going to have sex, we're
just going to be able to be together. So then the woman
doesn't get overly
excited. Anyway, so different answers to this. There's obviously it's a very
fascinating גמרא. Gemara. What's her name just came out with a book.
What's
her
name? That,
the woman in the, the MK, Ruth Calderon, right? Called Bride for
the Night or something like that, which is based, it's a collection
of her interpretations of various, like, rabbinic stories, but the one, but
one of them is this story. What? In English? Yes, in English,
yeah, Bride for the Night, something like that. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, אמר מר, Amar Mar, okay we did that. Okay, תנא, Tanna,
we taught, since we're dealing with רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov, one more statement of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר: Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer:
לא ישא אדם את אשה ודעתו לגרשה. Lo yisa adam et isha
v'daato l'garsha. A man should not marry a woman and be planning
or stay married to a woman or more probably have sex with
a woman, ודעתו, v'daato, I know it says ישא, yisa, but that's
the word, the whole marriage is already planning to divorce. But even
if, but even if it's not that, even if it's like just
staying married and having sex when you're planning on divorce, ודעתו לגרשה,
v'daato l'garsha, משום שנאמר, mishum shene'emar, but you're right, the statement is
don't get married with the intent of divorce, משום שנאמר: mishum shene'emar:
אל תחרוש על רעך רעה והוא יושב לבטח אתך. Al tachrosh al
re'acha ra'a v'hu yoshev lavetach itach. Don't be plotting against your
friend evil and he is living in confidence with you, in security
with you. So imagine the treachery of planning on divorcing your wife
and not saying anything and just staying in the marriage long because,
you know, you're still enjoying the benefits of the marriage. So obviously
you'd have to be transparent about what your intentions are. Okay, so
that was very interesting little whole digression, right? So it doesn't seem
like it's the same מסכת masechet that we were doing a week
ago, right? All right, moving on. Now we get to the question
of debate over property and over inheritance because we have this guy
who might be his father might be the first husband and his
father might be the second husband, right? Right, the case where the
brother-in-law did the יבום yibum and you don't know whose son he
is. Now there's also an interesting thing because who gets his father's
property? If he was his father's son, if he was ראובן's Reuven's
son, let's call them ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, okay? So you
have ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon and they've got and there's this
kid.
Here's ראובן, Reuven, okay,
here's שמעון, Shimon, I know ראובן's Reuven's married to רחל, Rachel, okay,
ראובן Reuven dies, שמעון Shimon has does questionable יבום yibum with רחל.
Rachel. Why is it questionable? Because somewhere during this period you've got
a kid and we'll call him רש"י Rashi because ראובן Reuven and
שמעון, Shimon, okay, that's what I just decided, we'll call him רש"י,
Rashi, okay, and he, you don't know who his father is. Is
his father ראובן? Reuven? Is his father שמעון? Shimon? Right? Now how
about ראובן's Reuven's property? Who gets ראובן's Reuven's property? If if this
was יבום, yibum, this would be his property. If this was יבום,
yibum, the property goes to שמעון, Shimon, right? If there was no
יבום yibum because he was ראובן's Reuven's kid, then the property goes
to the son. Who gets the property? So that's what we're going
to now discuss. The debate that the kid is going to have
with his possible father in terms of who gets the first guy's
property. So let's take a look. ספק ויבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי מיתנא.
Safek v'yavam shebau lachlok b'nichsei mitna. The ספק, safek, I'm calling him
רש"י, Rashi, the ספק safek and the יבם yavam that are coming
to divide בנכסי מיתנא, b'nichsei mitna, the property of the dead guy,
okay. ספק אומר, Safek omer, the ספק safek says: אנא בר מיתנא
הוא, Ana bar mitna hu, I'm the son of the dead guy,
I'm ראובן's Reuven's son, ונכסי דידי הוא, v'nichsei didi hu, and it's
my property. ויבם אומר, V'yavam omer, and the יבם yavam says: לא,
את ברי דידי את, Lo, at beri didi at, no, you're my
son, ולית לך ולא מידי בנכסיה, v'leit lach v'lo midi b'nichsei, and
you don't have anything with the property. So they both have an
equal claim. It's all riding on the question of whose son he
is. Nobody knows. הוי ממון המוטל בספק. Havay mamon hamutal b'safek. וממון
המוטל בספק חולקין. Umamon hamutal b'safek cholkin. It's money that is in
doubt, and when we don't know whose it is between the two
parties, we divide it. And sometimes there are other principles like you
go by the person who's מוחזק, muchzak, who's prior in possession. But
nobody here is prior in possession. ראובן Reuven was prior in possession.
שמעון Shimon and the kid are both equally not in possession and
they both are coming with an equal claim, so we divide the
property. Okay.
Now ספק ובני יבם שבאו לחלוק. Safek uvnei yavam shebau lachlok.
Let's say here, let's stop calling him רש"י, Rashi, I don't know
what we'll call him,
okay, גרשון, Gershon, we'll call him גרשון, Gershon, okay, that's got a
resh and a shin. Okay, now you've got his definite kids, which
are קהת ומררי, Kehat u'Merari, okay, and now they're coming to divide,
okay, these kids are coming to divide, who are they coming to
divide?
ספק ובני יבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי מיתנא. Safek uvnei yavam shebau lachlok
b'nichsei mitna. So they're coming to divide this property. Now how are
they coming to divide this property? Because ראובן Reuven died, שמעון Shimon
did יבום yibum and then he died immediately afterwards. And now we're
debating whose property this is. So he says, it's all mine, I'm...
Reuven's son. I get all of Reuven's property. They say, "No, no,
no, no. You're not Reuven's son, you're our brother. Our father got
Reuven's property, and then he died, so we each get a third.
You don't get it all, we each get a third."
And you'd be the בכור?
bechor? All right, let's not worry about that. Okay, so okay. So
that's what ספק ובני יבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי מיתנא. safek u'vnei yavam
sheba'u lachloke b'nichsei mishna. ספק אמר הוא גברא, safek amar hu gavra,
meaning that person, meaning me, בר מיתנא הוא, bar mishna hu, I'm
Reuven's son. ונכסי דידי הוא, u'nichsei didi hu, and it's my property.
בני יבם אמרי, bnei yavam amri, and the other the sons of
Shimon say, "No, אנת אחינו אנת, at achinu at, you are our
brother. ומנתא, u'manta, it's not mishna, ומנתא u'manta הוא דאית לך בהדן,
hu d'is lach b'hadan, you have a portion with us, you get
a third, but that's it." Okay, so what do you say? Does
he get all, does he get a third, do we split the
difference? So סברו רבנן קמיה דרב משרישיא למימר, savru rabanan kamei d'rav
mesharsheya l'meimar, so the rabbis in front of Rav Mesharsheya thought to
say: מתניתין היא, matnitin hi, it's our Mishnah. Not this Mishnah, another
Mishnah. דתנן, d'tnan, we taught in the Mishnah: הוא
אינו יורש אותם והם יורשים אותו. hu
eino yoresh
otam v'hem yorshim oto.
He doesn't inherit them and they inherit him. What's the case there?
The case there is the following. Let me just remind myself.
Right. Okay, so this is a case of the classic you don't
know who the father is, right? You have two brothers, Yehuda and
Levi. Okay, Yehuda died. Forget
יבום. yibbum. Forget Levi. They're unrelated, not brothers, excuse me. Yehuda and
Barak. Yehuda died, Devora married Barak.
But they
didn't wait three months.
Okay, and then there's a kid. Okay, so here's the kid. So
you don't know who the father is. Now each of these guys
has other kids. Okay, right? So here's Yehuda's two kids, here's Barak's
two kids,
okay, and Shimon doesn't know who its father is. Now Yehuda and
Barak are both dead. So Shimon goes over to Yehuda's kids and
says: "Give me a portion in Yehuda's estate." What do they say
to him? "You're Barak's kid." Okay, he goes over to Barak's kids
and says: "Give me a portion of your father's estate." What do
they say to him? "You're Yehuda's kid." So he gets nothing. Okay,
so that's the Mishnah. So let's take a look. So סברו רבנן
למימר מתניתין היא דתנן
הוא
אינו יורש אותם,
savru rabanan l'meimar matnitin hi d'tnan hu eino
yoresh otam, he doesn't inherit them, והם יורשים אותו. v'hem yorshim oto.
Now let's say Shimon dies. Okay, who gets Shimon? Who inherits from
Shimon?
So Yehuda's kids and Barak's kids get together and they split it
because a brother would inherit assuming there's no kids, right? If he
dies and there's no fathers and no kids, the brothers get it.
So if he dies, they split his property. But when he comes
to collect, right, from them, each one says, "Go to the other."
Okay, והם יורשים אותו. v'hem yorshim oto. והכא איפכא, v'hacha ipcha, and
here it's the opposite. התם אמרי ליה, hatam amri leh, over there
they say to him: אייתי ראיה ושקול, ayti ra'aya u'shkol, "You want
a portion in our estate, go bring a proof and collect, and
if you can't, get out of here." ושקול. u'shkol. הכא אמר
להו, hacha amar lehu, here he says to the brothers, אמר להו:
amar lehu: אייתי ראיה ושקלו. ayti ra'aya u'shklu. He says, "Look, I
definitely have a piece of this property. Either I have it all
because I'm Reuven's kid, or I got part of it because I'm
Shimon's kid. So I am the default guy in this property. If
you think you've got a portion in it, go prove your case.
And since you can't prove your case, I'm going to get it
all." That's what the rabbis think, that Gershon should get it all.
So אמר להו רב משרישיא, amar lehu Rav Mesharsheya, so Mesharsheya said
back to them: מי דמי? mi dami? You can't compare it. התם
אינהו ודאי ואיהו ספק, hatam inhu vaday v'ihu safek, in this case,
they are definite heirs and he, each person he goes to, he's
got a doubtful claim, right? And he doesn't know, so they push
him off. Okay. הכא אידי ואידי ספק. hacha idi v'idi safek. Here,
although it's true that he's got a definite portion in a third
of it, in terms of the rest of it, he's doubtful. Okay,
and the other way that רש"י Rashi points out is, he might
have a definite stake, but he doesn't know on the basis of
what. He says, "I got a stake in this property." "Yeah, but
on what basis? On Reuven's son or on Shimon's son?" So therefore
his whole claim, although he definitely has a stake, his whole claim
is uncertain. Whereas here they are definite heirs and definite heirs, and
he's the only one with an uncertain claim. Okay. אלא אי דמיא
אלא למתניתין, ela i damya ela l'matnitin, if you want something similar
to this Mishnah, it's not this case but the following case: להא
דמיא, l'ha damya, לספק ובני יבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי יבם גופיה. l'safek
u'vnei yavam sheba'u lachloke b'nichsei yavam gufei. This
you want to know what this is like? This is like, forget
Reuven's estate, this is like what happens when they're coming to divide
Shimon's estate. Okay, so what are they going to say to him?
What are these guys going to say to Gershon? Gershon's going to
say, "I'm your brother." They're going to say, "No you're not." And
they have a definite claim, they know why they're inheriting this. estate,
and he has a doubtful, that's just like this case. Get out
of here, you can't prove that you have a portion. בנכסי יבם
גופא Benichsei yavam gufah סבור לך דהתם אמי ליה sabor lach dehasam
ami leh אייתי ראיה דאחונא את ושקול ayti raya de'achuna at ushkol
and take.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's not—so this case is not
the case by ראובן, Reuven, and therefore what do you do in
this case by ראובן? Reuven? What do you do? So what would
we do? So I would say, if it were up to me,
I'd say give גרשון Gershon the third that he's definitely entitled to,
okay, because either way he'd get a third, he gets it all,
and the rest like you know sort of divide among them. Let's
see what רש''י Rashi says, take a look at רש''י Rashi and
we'll end with that. So
רש''י Rashi says like this:
ונראה בעיני Venireh be'einai says
רש''י, Rashi, the line starts with the word דלעל, dele'eil, I don't
know where to tell you what it is, it's like ten lines
under where it says משלי ג Mishlei Gimmel in the margin between
רש''י Rashi and the גמרא. Gemara. ונראה בעיני Venireh be'einai says רש''י,
Rashi, דהוא מנתא דקמודו ליה שקיל, dehu mantsa dekamodu leh shakil,
the portion that they concede he definitely gets at least a third,
that he takes. והאידך Ve'idach and the rest, הוי ממון המוטל בספק
וחולקין, havei mamon hamutal besafek vecholkin, הוא נוטל חצי ובין כולם החצי.
hu notel chetzi uvein kulam hachetzi. And regarding—so he gets definitely a
third because they'll concede that he gets a third. The rest he's
claiming all, they're claiming all, so the rest you divide. So the
first third he gets, and the second two-thirds, okay, they divide equally,
okay? He gets a third, and they get, and they get the
last third. All right? Is that clear? This they concede, so this
is the part they concede, this is the part that they—this is
the part they debate, and that part
you—he claims I get all of it, they claim—they claim you only
get a third, they claim you only get equal to us, so
the part that they debate they split and he winds up getting
two-thirds and they get a third.
Okay, more of these types of cases tomorrow.